LinkedIn: www.linkedin.com/in/gurusubramaniams GitHub: https://github.com/gurusubramaniam

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Architectural engineering leader who develops engineers through coaching, mentoring, and leading by example. Experienced in managing engineers across the entire stack. Managerial reputation for being accessible, helpful, and encouraging professional growth. Experienced in software delivery management, product and program management, and solution architecture. Excels at building systems while balancing time to market, usability, and technical architecture. Strategic and results-driven with a passion for problem-solving.

CORE COMPETENCIES

- 15+ years of hands-on experience in software delivery management, product and program management, solution architecture, and architectural leadership.
- 5+ years of experience working in a complex, matrixed organization, leading and mentoring teams, fostering an inclusive work environment, and encouraging personal and professional growth.
- 5+ years of experience building, leading, and managing diverse, high-performing teams.
- Ability to identify and implement new and creative solutions that align with business needs, enhance automation and increase efficiency.
- Proven ability to work through change and ambiguity, with a positive attitude and a willingness to adapt to new challenges.

RESPONSIBILITIES

- Host regular one-on-one sessions with the team providing ongoing coaching, mentorship, and career path.
- Provide written performance evaluations and compensation planning.
- Plan and track timelines for the team ensuring efficient project or program execution.
- Work with Talent Acquisition for targeted hiring efforts and allocate resources to different platforms based on the product requirement.
- Partner with senior engineers and Product Management to design new features, intelligent, user-friendly products maintaining core simplicity and optimization.
- Adapt and deploy software engineering processes and best practices for performant, scalable, and high-quality user experiences.
- Own end-to-end delivery of the product including back-end and front-end components and services.
- Exercise strong judgment in ambiguous situations.

SKILLS

Solution creation | Automation | Intuitive product development | Project management | Problem-solving | Team leadership

Diversity and inclusion | Consumer Onboarding | Performance & Talent Management | Change Management | Strategic Thinking

TECHNICAL SKILLS

React.js | Node.js | JavaScript | Redux | HTML5 / CSS3 | GraphQL/APIs | LESS | Webpack

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

PayPal – San Jose, CA

2011-2023

Engineering Manager - Level 2 | PayPal - Regulatory Change Management

Sep 2021 - 2023

- Led a team of 10 software engineers (Web, iOS, Android, Java, and QA), in planning and executing software development projects in cross-function collaboration with product, UX, and business stakeholders.
- Led product launch for 1099-K to collect SSN for compliance with new IRS law for non-compliant users.
- Led and managed project to add Israel, Russia, and Thailand operational licenses resulting in YoY revenue of \$40 mn.
- Consolidated multiple product workflows to reduce integration support by 50% and improve user conversion rate by 10%.
- Managed project for account balance provisioning (PayPal Balance) to access money during checkout and P2P transactions.
- Developed consistent CFPB disclosure and fee experience, allowing company to avoid \$25M user lawsuit.
- Provided architectural leadership and End to End solutions guidance to architects to ensure scalable and reusable software aligned with the company's technical and security standards.
- Played the role of Scrum Master, Collaborate with UX, Analytics, and Product team on product decisions and designs.
- Collaborated with peer engineering managers on identifying best practices, improved team processes, and scalable solutions with minimal coding that were used for alerting, and monitoring failures and errors in production for both front-end and back-end systems..
- Instituted 1:1 weekly meetings to align engineers' career paths with their interests.

- Built, led, hired and managed high-performance team of 18 software engineers (Web, iOS, Android, Java, and QA).
- Provided architectural, people leadership, and End to End technical solutions guidance for launch of Shopping Platform for 450M customers (React, LESS, Redux, Node.js).
- Integrated Honey shopping transaction and dispute process with PayPal ecosystem, improved user engagement from 20M to 70M, and saved consumers \$100M through a rewards redemption program in year one.
- Added 2,000 new validated offers from Honey to new coupon redemption checkout experience where coupon use increased by 1.5%.
- Developed new cashback points program redeemable through PayPal balance or gift cards.
- Managed resources, solutions, and delivery of web applications using React, LESS, Redux, Node.js, and back-end systems.
- Supported LTR and RTL (I10n) representation on web apps and ensured accessibility (a11y) and usable web apps by building testing into the software development and delivery process. This reduced engineering time by 25%.
- Reduced hiring cost by 20% and increased hiring velocity by 40% for in-demand engineers by partnering with leadership to source personnel from Canada, India, and Mexico.
- Ensured that the team had the necessary tools, resources, and infrastructure to be productive.
- Played the role of Scrum Master, Collaborate with UX, Analytics, and Product team on product decisions and designs.

Member of Technical Staff - Level 2 | PayPal - Onboarding

Mar 2019 - Apr 2020

- Led, mentored, and managed a 3-member team for the successful launch of the PayPal consumer onboarding experience available in 250 countries for 6 different onboarding workflows in a single year.
- Introduced the concept of "nano-sized" code, optimizing coding assets from 1.2 MB to 600 kb (~67kb zip) with versioning to create sharable isomorphic UI components. This "nano-code" promotes reusability, consistency, and modularity across different workflows.
- Implemented server-driven UI (using GraphQL back-end) to reduce overall engineering time by 75% (page design) and empower constituent app and product owners to run different experiments in different templates at the same time (multiple experimentation platforms) and update the UI for their consumers within hours (replacing week-long manual process) with minimal styling code changes and without having to release the entire web app.
- Reduced engineering effort by 30%, increased time to market by 50% and decreased production downtime by 30% by creating configuration-driven reusable components.
- Provided architectural leadership and an elegantly simple solution of configuration-driven reusable components for consumption by constituent upstream/downstream applications in the product ecosystem.
- Designed and embedded interaction analytics to parse and transform raw interaction data into structured data for analysis and action.

Member of Technical Staff - Level 1 | PayPal - Onboarding

Jul 2016 - Apr 2019

- Excelled as a mentor, lead, and key contributor in a 6-member team.
- Increased user conversion rate and developer productivity by pitching and implementing onboarding workflow unification.
- Reduced engineering time by 75% through a new architecture that supports flexible, easy-to-configure server-driven UI.

Software Engineer III | Consumer and Partner Onboarding

Mar 2014 - Jul 2016

- Modernized frontend stack from Dust.js to React.js using emerging technologies (React, Redux, and SASS). Built onboarding flows in Node.js from Java.
- Engaged with Consumer and Partner onboarding as a full stack javascript engineer.
- Increased user conversion and activation by adding card, bank, and credit flow to onboarding.

Senior User Interface Engineer II | Consumer Onboarding

Nov 2011 - Mar 2014

- Worked on Node.js, CSS3, and Dust.js, executed Rapid Prototyping and worked on user wallet app.
- Worked on user experiences for onboarding users and VDC, credit applications, BML, and debit applications.
- Introduced mobile user Checkout experiences using a rendering engine powered by a 3rd party company.

CSC – Chennai, India Software Engineer Oct 2006 - Oct 2011

EDUCATION